Guide to the Irish Immigration Reform Movement, Boston Chapter Records AIA.073
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Irish Immigration Reform Movement, Boston Chapter Records
1965-1992
1986-1989
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Glynn, Gregory
AIA.073
2.5 Linear Feet in 1 record carton, 3 manuscript box, and 1 oversize folder
The Irish Immigration Reform Movement (IIRM) was a grassroots organization established in 1987 whose primary objective was to legalize the status of undocumented immigrations from Ireland and 34 other countries adversely affected by America's 1965 Immigration Act. This collection documents the activities of the organization's Boston branch, which combined traditional grassroots activism with legislative lobbying to provide assistance to immigrants in the greater Boston area, leverage Irish American political influence, help shape U.S. immigration policy in the late 1980s, and energize the Irish American political presence in Washington. This collection consists of publications, artifacts, photographs, memoranda, correspondence, research files, congressional transcripts, newspaper clippings, and video footage collected by Gregory Glynn during the course of his involvement with the Boston, Massachusetts chapter of the IIRM. The bulk of the materials date between 1986 and 1989, and document the organization's advocacy and assistance efforts on behalf of Irish immigrants living in the greater Boston area, with an emphasis on providing assistance to immigrants on day-to-day concerns such a housing and employment. The collection also illustrates the organization's lobbying efforts, at both the local and national level, to introduce legislation and other federal policies to increase visa availability, change the immigration quota system, and provide more straightforward paths to legalization.
Arrangement
Files are arranged alphabetically.
Historical Note
The Irish Immigration Reform Movement (IIRM) was a grassroots organization established in 1987 whose primary objective was to legalize the status of undocumented immigrations from Ireland and 34 other countries adversely affected by America's 1965 Immigration Act. The IIRM ceased activities in 1992. The creator of this collection, Gregory Glynn, was a publicity officer and one of the founding members of the organization's Boston branch.
Working for legislative reform, the IIRM grew from a small New York-based group to a national organization with branches in Boston, Chicago, Philadelphia, Houston, Washington, Kansas City, San Francisco, and San Jose. The organization's Boston branch, dedicated to the needs of undocumented Irish immigrants in the Massachusetts area, was founded on August 26, 1987 and was located in Dorchester. Combining traditional grassroots activism with legislative lobbying, the IIRM leveraged Irish American political influence to influence U.S. immigration policy in the late 1980s and in the process energized the Irish American political presence in Washington.
The Immigration Act of 1990 (H.R. 4300) stands as the primary legislative legacy of the IIRM. This legislation provided a three-year transitional visa program through which 48,000 visas were granted to Ireland, as well as the annual diversity visa lottery program which continued into the 21st century.
Reflecting the IIRM's "all-Ireland" perspective, the transitional visa program contained a provision defining Northern Ireland as a separate state. This unique element, secured through intense lobbying by the IIRM, enabled thousands from Northern Ireland to participate in the visa lottery who, prior to this, had been ineligible because the United States' immigration system classified them as English.
The IIRM was also instrumental in securing 25,000 visas for Ireland through several extensions of the Donnelly Visa program from 1988 up to the implementation of the Immigration Act of 1990.
In order to address the day-to-day problems of documented as well as undocumented Irish at the time, IIRM members established the Emerald Isle Immigration Center (EIIC), which since 1988 has served as a model for similar advice and advocacy agencies in the United States. It operated New York City offices in Woodside, Queens and in Woodlawn, the Bronx.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Gregory Glynn in October 2014, with additional accretions donated by Glynn in June 2018 and August 2023. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 2014.179, 2018.113, and 2023.101.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of publications, artifacts, photographs, memoranda, correspondence, research files, congressional transcripts, newspaper clippings, and video footage collected by Gregory Glynn during the course of his involvement with the Boston, Massachusetts chapter of the Irish Immigration Reform Movement. The bulk of the materials date between 1986 and 1989, and document the organization's advocacy and assistance efforts on behalf of Irish immigrants living in the greater Boston area, with an emphasis on providing assistance to immigrants on day-to-day concerns such a housing and employment. These efforts were often carried out in collaboration with other agencies and organizations in the area, including advocacy groups focused on different immigrant communities. The collection also illustrates the organization's lobbying efforts, at both the local and national level, to introduce legislation and other federal policies to increase visa availability, change the immigration quota system, and provide more straightforward paths to legalization.
Related Materials
Irish Immigration Reform Movement, New York Branch Records (AIA 016)
Ireland House Oral History Collection (AIA 030)
Irish Echo Photographs (AIA 045)
Immigrants -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Irish Americans -- Politics and government.; Emigration and immigration law -- United States.; Immigrants -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; Irish Americans -- Politics and government -- Boston (Mass.); Irish Americans -- Boston (Mass.); Donnelly, Brian J. (Brian Joseph), 1946-; Kennedy, Edward M. (Edward Moore), 1932-2009; Glynn, Gregory; Irish Immigration Reform Movement
- Berman Visa Lottery, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Buttons and Stickers, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Center for Immigrant Rights, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Comitato Dell 'Emigrazione Italiana of Boston, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Communication with Irish Government and Opposition Parties, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Consulate General of Ireland, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1987-1991 (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
- Dail Eireann Remarks on Emigrants, Dec 8, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Flatley Company Letter to Mazzoli, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Flyers, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Funding Proposals, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Gateway Cities Funding Proposal, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- "Guide for the New Irish", 1988 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Holt, Miller, and Associates, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Immigration Reform and Control Act of 1986, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 11, Folder 10)
- Immigration Act of 1987 (H.R. 3143), 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 13, Folder 12)
- Immigration Committee and Legalization Task Force, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Incoming Mail, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Invoices, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Kennedy-Simpson Legal Immigration Reform Bill, circa 1989 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Kerry, John, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 16, Box 3, Folder 6)
- Letter to Attorney General Edwin Meese III, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Massachusetts Congressional Representatives, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Massachusetts Immigrant and Refugee Advocacy Coalition, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Massachusetts Immigration Committee, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Mayor Raymond L. Flynn Remarks Before U.S. Senator Judiciary Committee's Subcommittee on Immigration and Refugee Affairs, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- National Council, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Needs Assessment, Massachusetts Office for Refugees and Immigrants, circa 1988 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Newsletters, 1987-1989 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Newspapers and clippings, 1983-1991 (Box 1, Folder 21-23, Box 2, Folder 3, Folder 5, Folder 8, Folder 10, Folder 13, Folder 16, Box Shared Tamiment 031, Folder 11, Box 3, Folder 12, Box 4, Folder 3-36)
- Notes, circa 1988 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Office for Refugees and Immigrants, Feb 1, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Organization Overview, circa 1988 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Outgoing Mail, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Photographs, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 1, Folder 6)
- Publications, 1987-1992 (Box 2, Folder 2, Folder 4, Folder 7, Folder 9, Folder 11-12, Folder 15)
- Quotas, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Research, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Selective Service, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Statistical Yearbook of the Immigration and Naturalization Service (Department of Justice), 1987 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Television Programs, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
- Visas, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 31, Box 3, Folder 8)
- WROL, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 5)